<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The nightingale vvarbling forth her owne disaster; or The rape of Philomela. Newly written in English verse, by Martin Parker</title>
            <author>M. P. (Martin Parker), d. 1656?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08974</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19260</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110227</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845817</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845817</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10740</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08974)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10740)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1030:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The nightingale vvarbling forth her owne disaster; or The rape of Philomela. Newly written in English verse, by Martin Parker</title>
                  <author>M. P. (Martin Parker), d. 1656?</author>
                  <author>Ovid, 43 B.C.-17 or 18 A.D. Metamorphoses. Book 6.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G[eorge] P[urslowe] for William Cooke, and are to be sold at his shop neere Furnevals Inne gate in Holbourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Based on the story in book 6 of the "Metamorphoses" of Ovid.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C (-A1,C8).</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The rape of Philomel.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10740:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10740:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NIGHTINGALE WARBLING forth her owne diſaſter; OR <hi>The rape of Philomela.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Newly written in Engliſh verſe,</hi> By MARTIN PARKER,</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>G.P.</hi> for <hi>William Cooke,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop neere <hi>Furnevals Iune</hi> gate in Holbourne. 1632,</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10740:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10740:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE <hi>Henry Parker,</hi> Lord <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> and <hi>Mount Eagle,</hi> Baron of <hi>Ric,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou may (I confeſſe) accuſe me of petulancy and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding preſumption, in that I farre unworthy and altogether unknowne to your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
<pb facs="tcp:10740:3"/>
ſhould thus dare to attempt the Dedication of this my unpoliſht piece to one ſo eminent in judgment as your excellent Selfe, yet when I contemplate your vertues (whereof humility is chiefe) I am imboldned (in hope of your Honorable pardon) to preſent this Embrion of my weake braine to your iudicious view: deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring your Lordſhip to ſhew your ſelfe (as you hitherto have bin) the Patterne and Patron of curteſie in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting and remitting my booke and my boldnes: the antient Philoſophers did decipher a true Noble man by foure excellent qualities which are theſe: Firſt, A hauty courage in time of Martiall exerciſe. Secondly, A
<pb facs="tcp:10740:3"/>
heart to iudge. Thirdly, A hand to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eward: and Fourthly, Clemency to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rdon. I knowing your noble mind to be amply replete with all theſe v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtuous indowments, what wonder i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it that I have thus adventured the Poem, for the excellency of the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory (I confeſſe) did deſerve a more skillfull penman, being a Tragedy ſo unparaleld, that I wonder why none of our temporary Laureats have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken it before: but as I doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce to be advanced to the firſt place in this worke, ſo doe I more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly exult in that it finds ſo hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a Patron My Nightingale fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the hiſſing Serpents of this envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous age deſires your powerfull wings
<pb facs="tcp:10740:4"/>
to ſhelter her. And in lieu of your ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerous approbation of her ſong, my Muſe (by you her noble <hi>Mecaenas</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated) ſhall endevour heereaf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er with a Poſie of a ſweeter odour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o kiſſe the hand of your Honour. In t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> interim 'I remaine both in heart tongue and pen,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The devout adorer of your Lordſhips vertues.</hi> MARTIN PARKER</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10740:4"/>
            <head>To the Iudicious Reader, health.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Am not ignorant (courteous Reader) of the old adage; <hi>He that ſeeks to pleaſe all men, ſhall never finiſh his task;</hi> for there is no piec ſo accurately done, but ſome (either through ignorance or envie) will eſpie conceited faults in it; let <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles</hi> draw his picture with never ſo much art and iudgement the <hi>Cobler</hi> will find a hole in his coate; let an Author write as learnedly as <hi>Homer,</hi> were it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, he ſhall be ſubiect to the cavilling cenſure of <hi>Zoilus;</hi> no marvell
<pb facs="tcp:10740:5"/>
then if I the moſt unperfect vaſſall of the Muſes be ſcoft for my endeuour, when the beſt deſervings Artiſt is not free: but my hope is that though <hi>I</hi> be condemned by the ignorant <hi>Momus,</hi> or envious <hi>Critick,</hi> I ſhall be bayld by the learned and iudicious, to whom I only ſend my Booke: for the reſt, as they cannot be bar'd from reading, ſo I will not hinder them from their owne opinions: which when they have, their gaine is litle, and my loſſe is leſſe. If my <hi>Nightingales ſong</hi> pleaſe the honeſt and intellectuall man, ſhe hath her wiſh, for ſhe ſings not to pleaſe knaves and fooles: nor can they hurt her much: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they ſhoote her dead with the arrowes of aſperſion; but I thinke none is ſo inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane to hurt (much leſſe to kill) a <hi>Nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingale,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:5"/>
therefore ſhe is confident of her ſafety, and dares adventure into the world to warble forth her owne diſaſter. In her ſtory you ſhall finde ſuch woefull, wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and tragicall diſcourſe, that a heart of Adamant way find its invaliditie, like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Goates blood which hath the vertue to diſſolve it, when to all other meanes it is impenetrable. I have endeavored (as her Secretary) to pen her ſong, with as much skill as my little learning can produce, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in if I have pleaſed the fancy of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Reader, <hi>I</hi> have hit the white, and gaind the fruition of my hopes; if not, all my Poetry is quite kild in the egge. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, good Reader, for the love thou bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to the Muſes, iudge charitably now that <hi>I</hi> may be animated to proceede to thy
<pb facs="tcp:10740:6"/>
future profit and pleaſure. Which hoping thou wilt, doe <hi>I</hi> commit thee to the tuition of thy Maker, and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine, if now, ever hereafter, MARTIN PARKER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:10740:6"/>
            <head>The Author to his Booke, and it to him in manner of a Dialogue.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>POore harmeleſſe bird, how darſt thou undertake</l>
               <l>To leave the deſart woods and flye abroad,</l>
               <l>Mongſt thoſe that of thy ſong a ſcoffe will make,</l>
               <l>And poyſon execrate like to a toade</l>
               <l>What ever paines thy Penman hath beſtowd?</l>
               <l>One he miſlikes the phraſe, another will</l>
               <l>Say this word fits not well, that verſe runs ill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What though one overweening foole may finde</l>
               <l>Some faults produced from his fond conceite?</l>
               <l>For him I ſhall a thouſand meete more kind</l>
               <l>That will commend my ſong and give compleat</l>
               <l>Encomious to thee for thy travell great,</l>
               <l>For thou (though no great Clerke, yet) haſt ſo pen'd it,</l>
               <l>That twenty may find fault ere one can mend it.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:10740:7"/>
            <head>To my friend <hi>Martin Parker</hi> on his mournefull ditty, The rape of <hi>Philomel.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>ITs now in faſhion, he who hath brought forth</l>
            <l>With's pen an iſſue of his braines beſt worth,</l>
            <l>Before toth' larger ſtage he venture it,</l>
            <l>Will cloth't with begg'd or borrow'd rags of wit:</l>
            <l>Thy Nightingale needs none; yet ſhe ſhall have</l>
            <l>Theſe fragant branches, which the Muſes gave</l>
            <l>Her from their bower, to ſhrowd her ſelf among,</l>
            <l>From hiſſing Serpents that would ſpoyle her ſong.</l>
            <l>Theſe will to her be a delight of choyce,</l>
            <l>But give no diapazon to her voyce,</l>
            <l>To pleaſe the moderne fry of wit and fame:</l>
            <l>That bribe their Iudgments with the Authors name,</l>
            <l>And in the title-page conclude it ill,</l>
            <l>Becauſe it ſprung from thy obſcurer quill.</l>
            <l>On theſe ſet eaſie thoughts, her voyce ſhee'l raiſe</l>
            <l>To ſing this unjuſt rape; and thy juſt prayſe.</l>
            <byline>William Reeve.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:10740:7"/>
            <head>An Encomium on the Author and his worke.</head>
            <l>IS there leſſe paines or merit in tranſlation,</l>
            <l>Then of a Poem in his new creation?</l>
            <l>Or doth be leſſe the Laurell branch deſerve,</l>
            <l>That will the ſubiect of another ſerve?</l>
            <l>No ſure: the weapon by this Author us'd</l>
            <l>May by another eaſily be abus'd.</l>
            <l>He knew his owne invention, matter, end,</l>
            <l>His proper ſcope, whether his Muſe to tend</l>
            <l>His liberty was choyſe to runne, his field</l>
            <l>Was large, that he cach way himſelfe might weild.</l>
            <l>But thou in narrow bounds art now included,</l>
            <l>Thy Muſe being from her liberty ſecluded;</l>
            <l>Captive to thy Authors humour and thy quill</l>
            <l>Subiect to his ſubiect, method, and his will.</l>
            <l>Carpe not then <hi>Momus</hi> at anothers paines,</l>
            <l>On <hi>Naſo's</hi> Poem; ſince he ſufficient gaines</l>
            <l>Hath got already, eternizing his name,</l>
            <l>And memorie ſtill ecchoing forth his fame,</l>
            <l>For his invention of this mournefull ſong,</l>
            <l>Sadly tun'd forth by <hi>Philomela's</hi> tongue.</l>
            <l>His was the plaine ſong of this direfull ditty.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:8"/>The deſcant thine, moving each heart to pitty</l>
            <l>Sweet <hi>Philomela's</hi> rape, henceforth ſo long</l>
            <l>As inceſt, murders, cruelty and wrong,</l>
            <l>Revenge, and ſad <hi>Eryinnys</hi> here ſhall dwell,</l>
            <l>So long this ſtory forth thy praiſe ſhall tell.</l>
            <byline>I.S.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:10740:8"/>
            <head>To his ingenious friend <hi>M.P.</hi> Author of this Poem.</head>
            <l>I Often have admir'd thy fluent veine,</l>
            <l>Compoſing things of an inferiour ſtraine;</l>
            <l>But neither I nor any man could looke,</l>
            <l>For ſuch a piece from thee, as this thy booke.</l>
            <l>Wert thou a ſcholler then 'twere no rare newes,</l>
            <l>But being none can any Reader chuſe</l>
            <l>But wonder at thy ſmooth and haughty ſtile?</l>
            <l>Were I not ſure thou didſt this worke compile,</l>
            <l>I'd not beleev't; tuſh, common ſenſe doth ſhow it,</l>
            <l>Tis wit not learning, that can make a Poet.</l>
            <l>Proceed with boldneſſe then, and let men ſee,</l>
            <l>The Aganippean well doth ſpring in thee.</l>
            <byline>Da. Price.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="history_of_poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:10740:9"/>
            <head>The Argument of this Poem or Hiſtory.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAndion</hi> Prince of Athens (as the Roman Poet <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> writes) had two daughters, the eldeſt cald <hi>Progne,</hi> and the youngeſt <hi>Philomela;</hi> which <hi>Progne,</hi> being eſpouſed to <hi>Tereus,</hi> the young King of Thrace; lived in great tranquillity and happineſſe for the ſpace of five yeeres; in which time <hi>Progne</hi> (more fond than wiſe) deſired to ſee her ſiſter <hi>Philomela,</hi> and with hourely importunity filled the eares of her husband <hi>Tereus,</hi> ſo that he gave his conſent to fetch <hi>Philome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> and having gotten the forced conſent of her father (partly by her owne deſire to ſee her ſiſter) he carried her away, and in the ſhip began to attempt the conqueſt of her virginity; whom ſhe reſiſts, and ſtrives to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime with forcible arguments: but landing, he tooke her to a Graunge houſe that ſtood in his owne Country, and there perforce both raviſht and cut out her tongue leſt ſhe ſhould bewray his impiety; ſo goes home, and tells his Queene, that her ſiſter <hi>Philomela</hi> was dead: ſhe grieves; but he with aſſimulation pacifier her, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle miſtruſting any ſuch inhumane action as hee had done. But <hi>Philomela</hi> by her ſelfe (incloſed) wrought
<pb facs="tcp:10740:9"/>
her mind in an handkerchiefe, which by a Gentleman that came that way by chance, ſhe ſent to the Queene her ſiſter, who conceald her ſpleene, till ſhe found fit time of vindication: which occaſion ſoone offered in this manner: Jt was an annuall cuſtome in Thrace for women to goe ſtrangely diſguiſd about the country, to celebrate the feaſts of <hi>Bacchus;</hi> in this manner went <hi>Progne</hi> to the Graunge, and fetcht out her ſiſter <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mela,</hi> whom having brought to the Court privatly, ſhe afterwards invited her husband to a banquet, kild her young ſonne <hi>Itis,</hi> who was about three yeeres of age, and dreſſing him for meat ſet it before her husband <hi>Tere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us;</hi> who having eaten it, and the impious deed dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, the Poet will have them (as unworthy of humane ſhape) to be Metamorphoſed into birds. <hi>Philomel</hi> into a Nightingale, <hi>Progne</hi> to a Swallow, and <hi>Tereus</hi> to a Lapwing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note the morall and let the fiction paſſe as it is.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:10740:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10740:10"/>
            <head>THE RAPE OF PHILOMELA.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VVHen <hi>Tellus</hi> old by <hi>Hyems</hi> late oppreſt,</l>
               <l>Was pittied and reſcued by <hi>Ver,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And in her gorgeous mantle was new dreſt</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Flora</hi> kindly had beſtow'd on her;</l>
               <l>I that did health before all wealth prefer</l>
               <l>Walkt forth to take the benefit of th'ayre,</l>
               <l>Wherewith <hi>Ambroſia</hi> might not then compare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2</head>
               <l>And chancing to paſſe by a curious grove,</l>
               <l>Which Nature artificially had made,</l>
               <l>Excelling that wherein the <hi>Queene of love</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Her wanton toyes with her coy lover playd,</l>
               <l>Therein I ſtept my ſelfe a while to ſhade</l>
               <l>From <hi>Titans</hi> force, which then full South was got,</l>
               <l>Reflecting rayes that were exceeding hot.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:11"/>
               <head>3</head>
               <l>There as I lay repoſed on the ground,</l>
               <l>Delighted with its odoriferous ſmell,</l>
               <l>The heavenly Quiriſters about me round,</l>
               <l>Made muſicke which did pleaſe my ſenſes well:</l>
               <l>Eſpecially the lovely <hi>Philomel.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Vpon a hawthorne bough did warbling ſit,</l>
               <l>You that will heare her ſong attend to it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>4</head>
               <l>For by the figure cal'd <hi>Proſopopeie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ile tell het tale as though her ſelfe did ſpeake,</l>
               <l>You'l pardon give, if not ſo well as ſhee</l>
               <l>I paint her ſtory, for my braine's too weake,</l>
               <l>For ſuch a taske, yet I the ice will breake</l>
               <l>That others of more learning may indevour</l>
               <l>Further to wade in this deepe ſpatious river.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>5</head>
               <l>Then let your mindes ſuppoſe that you doe heart</l>
               <l>A virgin raviſht and depriv'd of tongue,</l>
               <l>For ſo the Nightingale that ſings ſo cleare,</l>
               <l>Was once, as <hi>Ovid</hi> long agoe hath ſung;</l>
               <l>You maydens, wives, and men that heare her ſong</l>
               <l>Regard it well for it concernes you all,</l>
               <l>Tis wofull, wonderfull and tragicall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:11"/>
               <head>6</head>
               <l>I was, ſaith ſhe, the daughter of a Prince</l>
               <l>Who rul'd the flouriſhing Athenian ſtate,</l>
               <l>I had a ſiſter that before nor ſince</l>
               <l>For ſhape and beauty hardly had a mate:</l>
               <l>Our father had no ſonne, ſo't pleaſed fate,</l>
               <l>Wee his two daughters did ſupport his age,</l>
               <l>Whom he maintain'd in princely equipage.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>7</head>
               <l>But ſee the mutability o'th world</l>
               <l>And worldly things; how apt wee are to fall</l>
               <l>From biſſe to bale; we to and fro are hurl'd</l>
               <l>From joy to woe, from liberty to thrall;</l>
               <l>Moſt know their birth, but none know how they ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Depart from hence? or where, or when, or how,</l>
               <l>No time is ours but that which we have now.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>8</head>
               <l>My ſiſters beauty was by blab-tongued fame</l>
               <l>Divulged and diſperſed farre and neere,</l>
               <l>The youthfull King of Thrace, <hi>Tereus</hi> by name,</l>
               <l>Though farre remote did of this <hi>Phoenix</hi> heare,</l>
               <l>And quickly left his realme and ſubjects deare,</l>
               <l>To come and ſee whether fame ly'd, or no,</l>
               <l>But ſeeing her, he ſaid, 'twas certaine ſo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:12"/>
               <head>9</head>
               <l>He wooed hard to have her for his mate,</l>
               <l>And got at laſt her (and our fathers) love;</l>
               <l>The nuptiall rites in princely pomp and ſtate</l>
               <l>Were ſolemniz'd, and like it was to prove</l>
               <l>A happie match: for either party ſtrove,</l>
               <l>Each other in affection to excell;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Terens</hi> lov'd <hi>Progne,</hi> ſhe lov'd him as well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
               <head>10</head>
               <l>In a ſhort time after the wedding day</l>
               <l>The Thracian King (having a care on's land)</l>
               <l>With his faire Bride from Athens ſayld away,</l>
               <l>And ſoone arrived where he did command:</l>
               <l>His dutious ſubjects on the ſhore did ſtand</l>
               <l>To welcome home their King, and far fetcht Queen</l>
               <l>With all magnificence that ere was ſeene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="11">
               <head>11</head>
               <l>Five yeeres theſe Princes (as they ought to doe)</l>
               <l>Did live and loue with mindes reciprocall,</l>
               <l>And then faire <hi>Progne</hi> (O why did ſhe ſo!)</l>
               <l>Deſir'd a thing which cauſed my downefall;</l>
               <l>Yet 'twas her love then blame not her at all.</l>
               <l>She did intreat her husband to fetch mee,</l>
               <l>Whom ſhee deſired ardently to ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="12">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:12"/>
               <head>12</head>
               <l>He willing to fulfill her fond deſire</l>
               <l>Hoyſt ſayles for Athens to fetch <hi>Philomel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whom for my beauty all men did admire,</l>
               <l>Coequall with my ſiſters truth to tell;</l>
               <l>But young when <hi>Tereus</hi> firſt in liking fell</l>
               <l>With her: when he came on faire Athens ſhore</l>
               <l>And told his tale, my Father mourned ſore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="13">
               <head>13</head>
               <l>Alas, alas, deare ſonne in law, quoth hee,</l>
               <l>What you propound will ſurely be my death,</l>
               <l>For if you take my <hi>Philomel</hi> from mee,</l>
               <l>Twill not be long ere I reſigne my breath,</l>
               <l>For there is nothing that is underneath</l>
               <l>The heavens, that I doe valew worth my Childe;</l>
               <l>O let mee not be of her ſight beguild!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="14">
               <head>14</head>
               <l>The pearled drops fell from his aged eyes</l>
               <l>Like rivolets, that his pale cheekes bedewd;</l>
               <l>O <hi>Tereus</hi> marke how old <hi>Pandion</hi> cryes,</l>
               <l>This ſorrow did preſage what woe inſewd;</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Tereus</hi> his petition ſtill renewd;</l>
               <l>Quoth he; I will as carefull of her be,</l>
               <l>As heaven I wiſh ſhould have reſpect to me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="15">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:13"/>
               <head>15</head>
               <l>Her will I cheriſh like my owne deare Child.</l>
               <l>And I was overwilling to goe ſee</l>
               <l>My ſiſter <hi>Progue,</hi> then the old man ſmild,</l>
               <l>Sweet Girle, if thou deſires to goe (quoth he)</l>
               <l>It ſomething mitigates my griefe for thee;</l>
               <l>Farewell my joy, but till thy ſafe returne</l>
               <l>My hourely exerciſe ſhall be to mourne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="16">
               <head>16</head>
               <l>Here take her <hi>Terens,</hi> and my bleſſing with her,</l>
               <l>Be carefull of her if thou wiſh mee life.</l>
               <l>Thus went the Wolfe and ſilly Lambe together:</l>
               <l>I towards my ſiſter, he towards his wife.</l>
               <l>O now alas, my ſenſes are at ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Whether I ſhould relate his monſtrous blame,</l>
               <l>Or hold my peace; and ſo ſave manhoods ſhame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="17">
               <head>17</head>
               <l>But fith I thus have undertooke the taske,</l>
               <l>I muſt proceed and tell the ſtory right,</l>
               <l>Wherein ſuch horrid deedes I will unmaske</l>
               <l>As may the Auditors with woe affright:</l>
               <l>O monſtrous caitiffe, arm'd with helliſh ſpight!</l>
               <l>No time before nor after ere could tell</l>
               <l>Of any deed that thine may paralell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="18">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:13"/>
               <head>18</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lucretia</hi> that Roman Lady had</l>
               <l>Great cauſe of woe; yet not ſo great as I,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Tarquin</hi> though his fact was worſe than bad</l>
               <l>In raviſhing the flower of chaſtity;</l>
               <l>He was no kin to her: but <hi>Tereus,</hi> thy</l>
               <l>Vnnaturall deed, can no way be excus'd</l>
               <l>For thou thy wives owne ſiſter haſt abus'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="19">
               <head>19</head>
               <l>When in his ſhip the Fox had got the Kid,</l>
               <l>Poore innocent, I dreading no ſuch ill,</l>
               <l>Againſt the lawes of gods and men he did</l>
               <l>Begin to tempt me to his lawleſſe will;</l>
               <l>But I, by vertue alwaies tutor'd, ſtill</l>
               <l>Defi'd him and his impious deſire,</l>
               <l>And us'd theſe words to quench his luſt-bred fire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="20">
               <head>20</head>
               <l>Ah brother <hi>Tereus,</hi> ſpring theſe words from jeſt</l>
               <l>To try my conſtitution? if they doe,</l>
               <l>I pardon them: but if your foule requeſt</l>
               <l>Be fram'd in earneſt; then I let you know,</l>
               <l>You are not as you ſeeme i'th outward ſhow;</l>
               <l>A man I thought you were by forme and ſtatute,</l>
               <l>But your interior parts ſhame humane nature.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="21">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:14"/>
               <head>21</head>
               <l>Haſt thou me raviſh'd from my fathers ſight,</l>
               <l>Pretending that my ſiſter for me ſent?</l>
               <l>And ſeek'ſt thou thus to rob her of her right,</l>
               <l>Whom once thou thoughtſt Natures chiefe ornament?</l>
               <l>Doſt thinke the gods would not thy will prevent?</l>
               <l>To wrong thy wife if thou in luſt doſt burne,</l>
               <l>Can none but her owne ſiſter ſerve thy turne?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="22">
               <head>22</head>
               <l>For ſhame leave off thy brutiſh enterprize,</l>
               <l>And let not future times ſpeake ſuch a thing,</l>
               <l>Even for thine honours ſake I thee adviſe,</l>
               <l>Stayne not the ſacred title of a King:</l>
               <l>Thinke what a ſcandall it to thee would bring<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Kings like the gods ſhould practiſe actions juſt</l>
               <l>Methinks this thoght ſhould que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch thy beſtial luſt</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="23">
               <head>23</head>
               <l>Theſe arguments (and many more as good)</l>
               <l>To him (paſt ſenſe) I did in vaine produce,</l>
               <l>My tongue more than my face inflam'd his luſt,</l>
               <l>All pious thoughts with him were out of uſe:</l>
               <l>No teares, no prayers, no reaſon, no excuſe</l>
               <l>Could pierce his boſome (made obdure with ſin;)</l>
               <l>Hee's now more fierce than when he did begin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="24">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:14"/>
               <head>24</head>
               <l>Yet in the ſhip his will he could not have</l>
               <l>Becauſe of thoſe which were within the ſame,</l>
               <l>Whereby (poore wretch) I had good hope to ſave</l>
               <l>That Iewell which he did unjuſtly claime:</l>
               <l>But more and more this helliſh fire did flame</l>
               <l>Therefore another courſe he tooke in hand;</l>
               <l>Being deny'd at Sea, he try'd on land.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="25">
               <head>25</head>
               <l>Charging his men upon his native ſoyle</l>
               <l>To land both him and mee: O, is't not ſtrange,</l>
               <l>That men ſhould worke ſo many waies to ſpoyle</l>
               <l>Their ſoules, when thus from vertues path they range?</l>
               <l>Now to be briefe, he brought me to a Graunge</l>
               <l>That ſtood remote from any towne or place,</l>
               <l>And there (perforce) he did my corps imbrace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="26">
               <head>26</head>
               <l>Which having done, I tore my amber treſſes,</l>
               <l>Rayling againſt the Panther truculent,</l>
               <l>And by my furious ſpleene the Tyrant gheſſes,</l>
               <l>Of his foule fact what would be the event;</l>
               <l>Therefore he thought his miſchiefe to prevent.</l>
               <l>And cauſe to none I ſhould bewray my wrong,</l>
               <l>He drew his knife and quite cut out my tongue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="27">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:15"/>
               <head>27</head>
               <l>Thus rape was ſeconded by cruelty,</l>
               <l>One vice another alwaies doth ſucceede</l>
               <l>When Satan hath mans heart in cuſtodie;</l>
               <l>By heavens ordinance it is decreed</l>
               <l>The reprobate cannot from bonds be freed,</l>
               <l>Till the full meaſure of his ſinne runnes o'r:</l>
               <l>Vice unrepented ſtill increaſeth more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="28">
               <head>28</head>
               <l>So this fell miſcreant, ſhame of his kind,</l>
               <l>Having by force ſtolne my virginity,</l>
               <l>Was loth to leave that inſtrument behind</l>
               <l>Which to the world might blaze his villanie:</l>
               <l>O monſtrous rape, perfidious treachery!</l>
               <l>What words ſhall I or any uſe t'expreſſe</l>
               <l>This mans (nay rather monſters) wickedneſſe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="29">
               <head>29</head>
               <l>Or unto whom may I him well compare?</l>
               <l>To th'Emperour <hi>Nero</hi> ſurely and no other,</l>
               <l>Who in this ſacrilegious kind did dare</l>
               <l>Inceſtuouſly to raviſh his owne mother,</l>
               <l>And after kild her: thou mayſt be his brother,</l>
               <l>For he that his wives ſiſter will deflower</l>
               <l>Would uſe his mother ſo were ſhe in's power.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="30">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:15"/>
               <head>30</head>
               <l>Now what becomes of me poore <hi>Philomel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Being left ſpoyld and mangled in this manner,</l>
               <l>I by my ſelfe (alone) am left to dwell,</l>
               <l>Where none mee knowes or heares of my diſhonour.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tereus</hi> goes to his Queene, and fawnes upon her,</l>
               <l>Patiently praying her his newes to brooke,</l>
               <l>For death her ſiſter <hi>Philomel</hi> had tooke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="31">
               <head>31</head>
               <l>She ſhriekes and cries with <hi>lachrimable</hi> meane,</l>
               <l>And by no meanes can pacified bee,</l>
               <l>Siſter, ſaith ſhee, alas, and art thou gone?</l>
               <l>I'le not be long before I follow thee.</l>
               <l>Deere love, ſet boundes unto thy griefe, quoth he,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt in me finde husband, father, ſiſter:</l>
               <l>With that, as <hi>Iudas</hi> did his Lord, he kiſt her.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="32">
               <head>32</head>
               <l>With theſe his ſubtle words of adulation,</l>
               <l>And many fained teares to force beliefe,</l>
               <l>The Queene at laſt left off her lamentation,</l>
               <l>Or at the leaſt gave limits to her griefe;</l>
               <l>Little miſtruſting him her boſome thiefe:</l>
               <l>O how hypocriſie can for a while</l>
               <l>Cover mens ſinnes, and Iudgments wit beguile!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="33">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:16"/>
               <head>33</head>
               <l>But ſuch foule crimes though in darke corners done</l>
               <l>When heaven doth ſee fit time, ſhall be reveal'd</l>
               <l>And open laid in the ſight of the Sun,</l>
               <l>Even when the Author thinks it's moſt conceal'd:</l>
               <l>So I having to the juſt gods appeal'd</l>
               <l>For juſtice and revenge at laſt did finde</l>
               <l>A meanes to fit the monſter in his kinde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="34">
               <head>34</head>
               <l>I with my needle ſhow'd my curious skill,</l>
               <l>A handkerchiefe with letters plaine I wrought,</l>
               <l>Which being finiſht (by <hi>Ioves</hi> ſacred will)</l>
               <l>Did publiſh what I in my boſome thought;</l>
               <l>A Gentleman by chance that way was brought,</l>
               <l>He having loſt his way i'th dead of night</l>
               <l>Found out this lodge, afarre off ſeeing light.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="35">
               <head>35</head>
               <l>Thither he rode, and at the window cal'd</l>
               <l>I priſoner like look't out, but could not tell</l>
               <l>With words my mind, yet how I came in thrall.</l>
               <l>And how abus'd, with ſignes I ſhow'd him well;</l>
               <l>He pittying me (wretched <hi>Philomel</hi>)</l>
               <l>The handkerchiefe wherein my mind was ſeene</l>
               <l>I threw to him to carry to the Queene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="36">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:16"/>
               <head>36</head>
               <l>He faithfully delivered his charge</l>
               <l>As did befit one whom he ſeem'd to bee;</l>
               <l>The Queene by this did underſtand (at large)</l>
               <l>My woe wrought by her husbands villanie;</l>
               <l>Yet what ſhe knew ſhe covered ſecretly,</l>
               <l>Vntill ſhe found a time revenge to worke;</l>
               <l>O marke what plots in womens minds do lurke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="37">
               <head>37</head>
               <l>For ſuch revenge (at length) ſhe wrought indeed</l>
               <l>As ſtaynes her ſex (as foule as be did his.)</l>
               <l>O that I might now from my taske be freed;</l>
               <l>I mourne for all the ſtory; chiefely this;</l>
               <l>I coadjutor was in her amiſſe:</l>
               <l>Ah now, methinkes, I heare ſome baſhfull dame</l>
               <l>Say, <hi>Philomel,</hi> fye, hold thy peace for ſhame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="38">
               <head>38</head>
               <l>To this I anſwere Twere a deed unjuſt,</l>
               <l>Seeing I haue ſo laviſh bin to tell</l>
               <l>Each circumſtance of <hi>Terous</hi> lawleſſe luſt,</l>
               <l>And barbarous cruelty, both ſprung from hell,</l>
               <l>To hide my ſiſters fault no <hi>Philomel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Proceed aright the ſecond part to ſing</l>
               <l>Of thy ſad ſong without diſſembling,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="39">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:17"/>
               <head>39</head>
               <l>And tell thine owne blame too, as well as hers</l>
               <l>So ſhalt thou not of falſhood be accus'd;</l>
               <l>Be bold for he or ſhe that truth prefers,</l>
               <l>(And loth to be by flattery abus'd</l>
               <l>If thou tell true) will hold thee more excus'd:</l>
               <l>Come briefly to't, or elſe thy long digreſſion</l>
               <l>Will lengthen out the liſt of thy tranſgreſſion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="40">
               <head>40</head>
               <l>Then this it is; when <hi>Progne</hi> (as I ſayd)</l>
               <l>Well underſtood where I her ſiſter was,</l>
               <l>She ſtudying how to have me thence convay'd;</l>
               <l>Marke what the Deſtinies ſoone brought to paſſe;</l>
               <l>It was a cuſtome through the realme of Thrace</l>
               <l>For women (like mad Bedlams forth to range</l>
               <l>About the country clad in garments ſtrange.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="41">
               <head>41</head>
               <l>In celebration of mad <hi>Bacchus</hi> feaſts</l>
               <l>(A geſture proper to his Deity,</l>
               <l>Whoſe power doth metamorphoſe men to beaſts,</l>
               <l>When w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of them hath got the maſterie)</l>
               <l>Among theſe <hi>Bachanalian</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ides went ſhee,</l>
               <l>I meane, my ſiſter; through which prete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>She came to viſit me with woe perple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="42">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:17"/>
               <head>42</head>
               <l>She tooke me from that place (diſconſolate)</l>
               <l>And brought me with her privately to th' Court;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tereus</hi> (miſtruſting no ſuch diveliſh hate,</l>
               <l>Nor that he was detected in ſuch ſort)</l>
               <l>Did entertaine his Queene with Princely ſport,</l>
               <l>And ſhe for him a ſumptuous feaſt did make:</l>
               <l>To tell what Cares ſhe got, my heart doth ake<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="43">
               <head>43</head>
               <l>Her owne deare Sonne) by <hi>Tereus</hi> on her got)</l>
               <l>Vnnaturally ſhe kil'd: Oh bloody beaſt,</l>
               <l>Nay, worſe than any beaſt! for they will not</l>
               <l>Suffer their yong of harme to taſte the leaſt,</l>
               <l>This Banquet did excell <hi>Lycaons</hi> feaſt;</l>
               <l>For here a Mother of her Sonne made meat,</l>
               <l>Which his owne Father greedily did eat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="44">
               <head>44</head>
               <l>Oh flinty-hearted <hi>Progne!</hi> what although</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tereus</hi> offended thee beyond compare,</l>
               <l>Could nothing ſerve but to requite him ſo?</l>
               <l>Hadſt thou not in thy child the greateſt ſhare,</l>
               <l>Which in thy body thou nine moneths didſt beare?</l>
               <l>Yet blaming thee, I muſt my ſelfe condemne,</l>
               <l>For I conſented to the death of him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="45">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:18"/>
               <head>45</head>
               <l>The pretty Infant ſeeing her to ſit</l>
               <l>So penſively (as one depriv'd of joy)</l>
               <l>He runs to her (according to his wit)</l>
               <l>And askes the cauſe of her ſo ſad annoy:</l>
               <l>Mother (ſaith he) am I not your beſt boy?</l>
               <l>Come kiſſe me then; and Ile goe call my Dad,</l>
               <l>To come and play with you, and make you glad.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="46">
               <head>46</head>
               <l>But ſhe (not like a Woman, but a Tyger)</l>
               <l>Did caſt him from her in diſdainefull wiſe,</l>
               <l>Then did ſhe take him (Oh unheard-of rigour!)</l>
               <l>And cut his head off: this could not ſuffice,</l>
               <l>But of his little limbs ſhe made mine'd pies,</l>
               <l>Which at the banquet was the chiefeſt diſh:</l>
               <l>Thus curſed <hi>Tereus</hi> fed on his owne fleſh.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="47">
               <head>47</head>
               <l>This barbarous action gives the world good cauſe</l>
               <l>To enter into conſultation juſt,</l>
               <l>For ſurely none can tell, without great pauſe,</l>
               <l>Which fact was worſt: or <hi>Tereus</hi> beaſtly luſt,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Pragnes</hi> monſtrous murther. Sure I muſt</l>
               <l>Cenſure her deed oth' two to be the worſt,</l>
               <l>To kill her infant whom ſhe bare and nurſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="48">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:18"/>
               <head>48</head>
               <l>He that upon his foe would vengeance take</l>
               <l>And in moſt wrathfull manner wreak his ſpleene)</l>
               <l>Let him a woman of his counſell make,</l>
               <l>Their hearts moſt cruell are, as may be ſeene</l>
               <l>By the relation of this furious Queene.</l>
               <l>Fye, <hi>Philomel,</hi> thou wilt thy ſelfe abuſe,</l>
               <l>If for her ſake thou all her ſex accuſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="49">
               <head>49</head>
               <l>Tuſh, why ſhould I be partiall in this caſe,</l>
               <l>I'l tell the truth; and yet I doe not ſay,</l>
               <l>Though this one woman did her ſex diſgrace,</l>
               <l>That others imitate her wicked way;</l>
               <l>And yet, alas, too many goe aſtray</l>
               <l>In theſe laſt times; for Infants every yeere,</l>
               <l>Are by their mothers murthered (as I heare.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="50">
               <head>50</head>
               <l>Which makes me to take up a juſt complaint</l>
               <l>Againſt the female ſex for cruelty,</l>
               <l>And as my owne diſaſter I doe paint,</l>
               <l>Procured by my brothers luxurie</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en ſo I have, (and tis but equitie)</l>
               <l>Demonſtrated, or will ere I have done,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Progne's</hi> foule crime in killing her owne ſonne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="51">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:19"/>
               <head>51</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tereus</hi> having well fed, calls for young <hi>Jtis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Deere Queene, where is my little boy, quoth he,</l>
               <l>In whom next thee my temporall delight is?</l>
               <l>I thinke he's neere enough to you, quoth ſhee,</l>
               <l>Neerer than he is now he cannot be:</l>
               <l>Much good may't doe you Sir, for you have eate,</l>
               <l>I tell you true, no ordinary meate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="52">
               <head>52</head>
               <l>With that I <hi>Philomel</hi> that ſtood unſeene,</l>
               <l>Behind a cloath of arras, with the head</l>
               <l>O'th infant, given me by my ſiſter Queene,</l>
               <l>Step'd forth, and hearing what before ſhe ſaid,</l>
               <l>Of the event I nought at all did dread,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Tereus</hi> more might ſee his wretched caſe</l>
               <l>I threw the head of <hi>Jtis</hi> in his face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="53">
               <head>53</head>
               <l>Looke how a Lion, rouſed from his ſleepe,</l>
               <l>Runnes furiouſly 'gainſt thoſe did him wake;</l>
               <l>So <hi>Tereus</hi> to the heart was ſtruck ſo deepe,</l>
               <l>That more than terror made his joynts to quakes</l>
               <l>O wife, quoth he, what vengeance didſt thou take?</l>
               <l>'Twas I offended, why didſt not kill mee?</l>
               <l>As for young <hi>Jtis</hi> what offence did hee?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="54">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:19"/>
               <head>54</head>
               <l>Was he not thine owne fleſh aſwell as mine?</l>
               <l>How hadſt thou then the heart to ſee him bleed?</l>
               <l>My fault (I doe confeſſe) was great, but thine</l>
               <l>As far and more from nature doth exceed,</l>
               <l>No woman ever did ſo vile a deed:</l>
               <l>Oh how am I accurſt of all that be,</l>
               <l>I have devour'd what was begot by me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="55">
               <head>55</head>
               <l>But I his guiltleſſe death will vindicate,</l>
               <l>On both your bodies, (monſters that you are.)</l>
               <l>This ſaid, he did no time procraſtinate,</l>
               <l>But drew his ſword, and both our deaths did ſweare,</l>
               <l>Becauſe in the childs death we both had ſhare.</l>
               <l>Mine was the wrong at firſt, yet I confeſſe,</l>
               <l>I muſt plead guilty, though my fault was leſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="56">
               <head>56</head>
               <l>We fled his fury, he with ſword in hand,</l>
               <l>Purſu'd us, armed with revenge and ſteele;</l>
               <l>But heavenly powers, that had my wrongs well ſcan'd</l>
               <l>(Though we were worthy) would not let us feele</l>
               <l>The ſtroke of death: all three from head to heele</l>
               <l>Transformed were (if you'l truſt <hi>Ovids</hi> words)</l>
               <l>From humane Creatures unto ſenſeleſſe Birds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="57">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:20"/>
               <head>57</head>
               <l>I <hi>Philomel</hi> (turn'd to a Nightingale)</l>
               <l>Fled to the woods, and 'gainſt a bryer or thorne,</l>
               <l>I ſit and warble out my mournfull tale:</l>
               <l>To ſleepe I alwaies have with heed forborne,</l>
               <l>But ſweetly ſing at euening, noone, and morne.</l>
               <l>No time yeelds reſt unto my dulcide throat,</l>
               <l>But ſtill I ply my lachrimable note.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="58">
               <head>58</head>
               <l>My ſiſter <hi>Progne</hi> metamorphos'd was</l>
               <l>Into a Swallow (as the Poet ſayes:)</l>
               <l>Both of us all the Winter time doe paſſe</l>
               <l>Vnſeene of any, till <hi>Hyperious</hi> rayes</l>
               <l>Increaſe in hot influence, and the dayes</l>
               <l>Are drawne in length by Natures annuall courſe,</l>
               <l>The Swallow is a ſigne of Summers force.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="59">
               <head>59</head>
               <l>Vpon her breaſt her marke of guilt ſhe beares,</l>
               <l>Her back, head, wings and traine doe mourne in fable,</l>
               <l>No pleaſant note ſhe ſings, as any heares,</l>
               <l>But ſounds forth accents fad and untunable,</l>
               <l>Her fleſh unfit to furniſh any table,</l>
               <l>And if in any's hand ſhe chance to dye,</l>
               <l>'Tis counted ominous I know not why.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="60">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:20"/>
               <head>60</head>
               <l>In ſigne of her unnaturall cookery,</l>
               <l>Within a ſmokie Chimney ſtill ſhe builds,</l>
               <l>While I (with other Birds) abrod doe flye,</l>
               <l>In pleaſant woods, forreſts, and fragrant fields:</l>
               <l>My tune a comfort unto mankind yeelds.</l>
               <l>When April comes, then Country milkmaids long</l>
               <l>And ſtrive to heare the Nightingales ſweet ſong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="61">
               <head>61</head>
               <l>Yet ſtill alone I love to ſit and ſing,</l>
               <l>Delighted beſt in melancholy ſhade:</l>
               <l>My Harmony doth make the woods to ring:</l>
               <l>And by ſome learned Clerkes it hath been ſaid,</l>
               <l>That if a ſnake (whereof I am afraid)</l>
               <l>Should me devoure, a Scorpions forme ſhee'l take</l>
               <l>Which to prevent, I keepe my ſelfe awake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="62">
               <head>62</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tereus</hi> was made a Lapwing, he doth cry</l>
               <l>For his ſonne <hi>Jtis,</hi> as aloft he flyes,</l>
               <l>Which words being reverſt, doe ſignifie</l>
               <l>'Tis I; who by one horrid enterpriſe,</l>
               <l>Did cauſe ſuch floods of miſchiefe to ariſe:</l>
               <l>My wife, her ſiſter, and my owne deare child,</l>
               <l>I have quite overthrone, oh monſter vild!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="63">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:21"/>
               <head>63</head>
               <l>Vpon his head a tuft of feathers grow,</l>
               <l>A ſigne of Regall ſtate, which he did wrong<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>And if you marke his nature, it doth ſhew</l>
               <l>His ſordid deeds, for he delights in dung:</l>
               <l>He hath a bill exceeding ſharp and long,</l>
               <l>A figure of that knife (it ſeemes to be)</l>
               <l>Wherewith he did cut out the tongue of me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="64">
               <head>64</head>
               <l>Thus all of us were reſt of humane ſhape,</l>
               <l>A juſt reward for our inhumane deeds:</l>
               <l>All this was firſt occaſion'd by the rape</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Philomel:</hi> Rape further miſchiefe breeds,</l>
               <l>The nature of theſe birds who-ever reads,</l>
               <l>Shall finde ſo correſpondent to my words,</l>
               <l>That no vaine ſyllable my ſong affords.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="65">
               <head>65</head>
               <l>When old <hi>Pandion</hi> heard this tragicke newer,</l>
               <l>You will not marvell if I ſay he wept,</l>
               <l>All tranſitory joyes he did refuſe,</l>
               <l>And ſpent thoſe houres wherein he ſhould have ſlept,</l>
               <l>In ſobs and grones, which him awake ſtill kept;</l>
               <l>Ah miſerable man, methinks I ſee</l>
               <l>The character of <hi>Priam</hi> now in thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="66">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:21"/>
               <head>66</head>
               <l>Alas, ſaith he, you gods why are you ſo</l>
               <l>Vnkind, to let me live againſt my will?</l>
               <l>Why am I kept more miſery to know?</l>
               <l>More, ſaid I: no, that cannot be; yes ſtill,</l>
               <l>To beare the burden of ones former ill</l>
               <l>Addes every houre more horror to the heart,</l>
               <l>Nothing but death can caſe my carefull ſmart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="67">
               <head>67</head>
               <l>I that within few yeeres was ſo inrich'd,</l>
               <l>As no Prince could be more with daughters twaine,</l>
               <l>Which at an inſtant both away are twitch'd</l>
               <l>With Son in law, and grandchild; none remaine:</l>
               <l>Why then doth time procraſtinate my paine?</l>
               <l>Ah <hi>Philomel,</hi> thou and the little boy;</l>
               <l>Above the reſt procure my ſad annoy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="68">
               <head>68</head>
               <l>VVretch that I was, why did I ſuffer thee</l>
               <l>To goe with that capritious raviſher?</l>
               <l>Had I at home detain'd thee ſtill with mee,</l>
               <l>Thou mighteſt have bin now ſafe; could I preferre</l>
               <l>The ſly perſwaſions of a flatterer</l>
               <l>Before my care paternall over thee:</l>
               <l>The world may ſay the greateſt fault's in me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="69">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:22"/>
               <head>69</head>
               <l>No father, ile excuſe thee: for no harme</l>
               <l>Thou meant'ſt to mee, nor would'ſt have let me goe,</l>
               <l>But I (as well as <hi>Tereus</hi>) did thee charme,</l>
               <l>VVith oyly words: lov'd my ſiſter ſo,</l>
               <l>And that fond love was cauſe of this my woe:</l>
               <l>VVho would have thoght her husband could have bin</l>
               <l>So impious to attempt that horrid ſinne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="70">
               <head>70</head>
               <l>The aged Prince having with languiſhment</l>
               <l>A little while inforcedly drawne breath,</l>
               <l>His gray haires were to th'earth with ſorrowes ſent,</l>
               <l>Never went man more willing to his death;</l>
               <l>His living vertues wonne a Cypreſſe wreath:</l>
               <l>And his true loving ſubjects with ſalt teares</l>
               <l>VVatred his Sepulcher for many yeares.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="71">
               <head>71</head>
               <l>The reaſon why the Poet ſayes wee three,</l>
               <l>I, and my ſiſter, with her husband were,</l>
               <l>Transformed into birds, was cauſe that we</l>
               <l>Were all unworthy humane ſhapes to beare,</l>
               <l>As by our deedes prodigious doth appeare:</l>
               <l>The morall of the ſtory is the chiefe,</l>
               <l>As for the changing formes 'tis paſt beliefe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="72">
               <pb facs="tcp:10740:22"/>
               <head>72</head>
               <l>Yet there's no doubt but I poore <hi>Philomel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Have nothing ſung but what you may believe;</l>
               <l>Birds ſeldome uſe any untruthes to tell,</l>
               <l>If you'l not take my warrant I ſhall grieve;</l>
               <l>Whether you doe or no let me perceive</l>
               <l>That you all ſhun the vices mention'd in't,</l>
               <l>Then ile rejoyce becauſe my ſong's in print.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
